Guide to the Clark Leonard Hull Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Clark Leonard Hull papers
1902-1951
MS 294
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.25
(14 boxes)
The papers consist of manuscripts, research and laboratory notes, and class outlines by Clark Hull on behaviorism, hypnosis, childhood, reasoning and other topics in psychology. Of special interest are a series of twenty-eight notebooks (1915-1951) containing "original ideas on things in general." Also included are papers and theses by his students (1921-1940). Among the personal papers are two diaries (1902 and 1929, respectively) and a day-by-day record of his daughter's first two years, 1916-1917.
Hull, Clark Leonard, 1884-1952
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 106 instead of the originals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated through a series of gifts from Clark L. Hull in 1953; Mrs. Clark Hull in 1963; and Mrs. Ruth Hull Low in 1977.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection also available on microfilm (7,816 frames on 10 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM106.
Biographical / Historical
Clark Leonard Hull was an assistant professor of psychology at Yale University from 1920-1922; an associate professor from 1922-1925; and a professor from 1925-1952. He was the author of eight books and many articles.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of manuscripts, research and laboratory notes, and class outlines by Clark Hull on behaviorism, hypnosis, childhood, reasoning and other topics in psychology. Of special interest are a series of twenty-eight notebooks (1915-1951) containing "original ideas on things in general." Also included are papers and theses by his students (1921-1940). Among the personal papers are two diaries (1902 and 1929, respectively) and a day-by-day record of his daughter's first two years, 1916-1917.
Behaviorism (Psychology); Child development; Child psychology; Hypnotism; Psychology; Psychologists; Hull, Clark Leonard, 1884-1952; Yale University -- Faculty
- WRITINGS AND RESEARCH NOTES, 1902-1951
  - Aptitude tests, principles and methods of determining vocational and other specific attitudes, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Behaviorism, seminar notes, Vol. I, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Behaviorism, seminar notes (theoretical), Vol. II, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Behaviorism-"Habit and adaptive behavior" - plans and outlines for a major work, 1 vol., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Character experiments, 1 vol., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Childhood, psychological studies concerning, 1 vol., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Concepts, Ideas on, Vol. I and II, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Diary, personal, 1 vol., 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Diary, personal and notes, 1 vol., 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Experimental course, notes on, 1 vol., 1919 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Feeble minded, the problem of the," student paper by Hull, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hypnosis:
    - Experiments, notes on: Hypnotic seminar, Vol. I, July, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Outline plans for book, Vol. II, October, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Plans for book, Vol. III, August, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hypnotic research, Vol. IV, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hypnosis, outline for book, Vol. V, November, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Idea Books:
    - I: Original ideas on things in general (volume title reads "Original ideas in Psychology, etc."), 1915-1916 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - II: Original ideas on things in general, 1916-1918 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - III: Original ideas on things in general, 1918, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - IV: Original ideas on things in general, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - V: Original ideas on things in general, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - VI: Original ideas on things in general, 1923-[1924] (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - VII: Original ideas on things in general, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - VIII: Original ideas on things in general, 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - IX: Original ideas on things in general, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - X: Original ideas on things in general, 1927-1928 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - XI: Original ideas on things in general, 1927-1928 [1930] (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - XII: Ideas on things in general, 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - XIII: Ideas on things in general, 1931-1933 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - XIV: Ideas on things in general, 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - XV: Ideas on things in general, 1934-1935 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - XVI: Ideas on things in general, 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - XVII: Ideas on things in general, 1936-1937 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - XVIII: Ideas on things in general, 1937-1938 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - XIX: (Box 6, Folder 34)
      General
      see: box 11, folder 82
    - XX: Ideas on things in general, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - XXI: (Box 6, Folder 35)
      see: box 11, folder 83
    - XXII: Ideas on things in general, 1941-1943 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - XXIII: Ideas on things in general, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - XXIV (Box 6, Folder 37)
      see: box 11, folder 84
    - XXV: Ideas on things in general, 1946-1948 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - XXVI: Ideas on things in general, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - XXVII (Box 7, Folder 39)
      see: box 11, folder 85
    - XXVIII: Ideas on things in general, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Infancy, Psychological Study of Ruth Trask Hull
    - Vol. I, August, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Vol. II, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Insanity, ideas on, 1 vol., 1915-1916 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Introductory psychology, notes on, 1 vol., undated (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Laboratory research notes, 1 vol., 1930-1932 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Learning, psychology of - notes on the writing of a book concerning, 1 vol., 1934, 1938, 1948-1949 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Mathematical statistics, 1925; experimental psychology, notes on a revised course, 1927, 1 vol., 1925, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Medical psychology and German - English vocabulary, notes on, 1 vol., 1915 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Newspaper - reading research, 1 vol., undated (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Paper, ideas on, 1 vol., 1915 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Reasoning, psychology of, seminar notes, 1 vol., 1924 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Research in psychology, 1 vol., 1913 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Research notes, 2 notebooks, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Research notes, Weld, Maine, 1 vol., 1947 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Research projects, 1941-1942 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Research projects, 1943-1944; and research notes, personal, 1934-1935, 1934-1935, 1943-1944 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - "The Saints": A study of a fanatical rural sect. Student paper by Hull. (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Seminar notes, Institute of Human Relations, 1 vol.: see Add, 10/17/77 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Student research and theses, notes on:
    - 1921-1922 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - 1922-1925 (Box 8, Folder 59-61)
    - 1925-1927 (Box 9, Folder 62-63)
  - Student research:
    - 1927-1928 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - 1928-1929 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - 1929-1932 (Box 9, Folder 65-67)
  - Student and other directed research:
    - 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - 1934-1940 (Box 10, Folder 70-74)
  - Theoretical notes, Lewin notes, 1 vol., undated (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - Tobacco, experimental investigation of the effects
    - Vol. I, June, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - Vol. II, November, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Vol. III, October, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 78)
  - Vocational psychology, outline, 1 vol., undated (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - Vocational psychology, engineering shop tests, 1 vol., undated (Box 10, Folder 80)
- ADDITION 10/17/77, 1936-1951; (1 box, 5 volumes)
  Scope and Contents
  Donor: Mrs. Ruth Hull Low
  - Seminar notes, Institute of Human Relations, 1 vol., 1936 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - Idea Books:
    - XIX: ideas an things in general, 1938-1939 (Box 11, Folder 82)
    - XXI: ideas on things in general, 1940-1941 (Box 11, Folder 83)
    - XXIV: ideas on things in general, 1944-1946 (Box 11, Folder 84)
    - XXVII: ideas on things in general, 1949-1951 (Box 11, Folder 85)
- Additional Material, Accession 1982-M-001
  - Psychology 106 memoranda, 1936-1940 (Box 12, Folder 86-87)
  - Essays:
    - "The Conditioned Reflex,", 1933 (Box 13, Folder 88)
    - "Some Implications of the Goal Gradient and the Habit-Family Hypotheses for the Behavior of Young Children" (Box 13, Folder 89)
  - Reprints and papers, 1926-1942, undated (Box 14, Folder 90-91)